Guide to the David Dinkins Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
David Dinkins Papers,
1941-2001
[Bulk Dates: 1985-1993].
Dinkins, David N.
91 linear ft. (160 document boxes, 12 flat boxes, 5 index card boxes, 4 poster boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
MS#1441
6058659
These papers comprise correspondence, organizational records and documents, speeches, public schedules, photographs and memorabilia relating to the public life of David N. Dinkins, civil servant to the City of New York for over thirty years and professor in the Practice of Public Affairs at the Columbia University School of International and Public Affairs.
Biographical Notey
David N. Dinkins was born in Trenton, New Jersey on July 10, 1927. In his early childhood, Dinkins moved with his mother to Harlem, but returned to Trenton to attend high school. After graduating he enrolled in Howard University in Washington, DC. World War II erupted and his studies were put on hold when he served in the United States Marine Corps. After serving as a Marine during World War II, he went on to obtain his bachelor's degree in mathematics from Howard University in 1950. At Howard, he became a member of Alpha Phi Alpha fraternity, the nation's first intercollegiate fraternity for African-American men. After graduating from Howard, he married Joyce Burrows, a former classmate. They moved to Harlem in 1951 and in 1956 he graduated from Brooklyn Law School. Dinkins practiced law in New York City from 1956 until 1975, while pursuing a career in politics.
Joyce Burrows grew up in a very political family. Her father was Daniel Burrows, a former assemblyman and district leader. Burrows introduced Dinkins to J. Raymond Jones, the "Harlem Fox", known leader of Tammany Hall, the New York Democratic County Organization in the 1960s. It was through Jones that Dinkins became an integral part of the Carver Democratic Club. During this period he mixed and aligned himself with an influential group of upcoming politicians that included Charles Rangel, Percy Sutton and Basil Paterson. Later, this group of young and ambitious politicoes became known as the "gang of four".
In 1965, Dinkins was elected a New York State assemblyman. In this role he helped with the creation of the Search for Education, Elevation, and Knowledge Program (SEEK) in the City University of New York. SEEK assisted low income students with attaining a college education by helping them with basic education and counseling. As the program grew it became clear that many students could not stay in college without additional income. As a result, Dinkins mobilized the New York Urban Coalition and the 100 Black Men, organizations with core missions to educate youth through a variety of support services providing part time and summer jobs for students through agreements with private businesses.
Dinkins served as president of the Board of Elections from 1972-1973, successfully establishing guidelines that facilitated and encouraged wider voter registration. He convinced the legislature to allow voter registration by mail in New York State. At the same time, he convinced corporations, community groups, schools and unions to make voter registration forms readily available to the public. He went on to serve as city clerk from 1975 until 1985.
When Manhattan Borough President, Percy Sutton stepped down in 1977 to run for mayor of New York City, he encouraged Dinkins to run for the vacant position. Dinkins lost the first election to democratic candidate Andrew Stein, but won on his third attempt, in the 1985 campaign.
In 1989 Dinkins ran for mayor, defeating three-term incumbent Mayor Ed Koch, for the Democratic nomination. In November, he beat republican candidate and United States attorney, Rudy Giuliani, winning the general election. On January 1, 1990, Dinkins was sworn in as the first African American mayor of New York City. Dinkins was considered moderate and soft spoken in leadership style. When he took office, New York City was experiencing the effects of an economic recession; racial strife, drug use and crime were on the rise. Dinkins celebrated New York City as a "gorgeous mosaic" referring to its ethnic diversity, while pledging to mend racial tensions. And as the federal government had cut monetary aid to the nation's cities, Dinkins' supporters pushed an agenda that focused on social services for a struggling city population.
Dinkins promises to mend the city's race and religious divisions had to be balanced against a dire financial deficit. Nonetheless, Dinkins focused on making New York City a better place for its residents. He concentrated on AIDS prevention-treatment, fighting drug abuse, and building better schools and affordable housing. "Safe Streets, Safe City" was his criminal justice plan, which reduced crime while at the same time providing youth programs, expanding opportunities for children. He is credited with the creation of the office of Special Commissioner of Investigation for Schools, and worked to create an all civilian police complaint review board.
In 1991, a riot broke out between the Hasidic and Black communities in Crown Heights, Brooklyn. In its aftermath, some thought that the Hasidic community received favored treatment, while others thought that not enough force was used against the Black community. In 1993, Dinkins lost the mayoral race to Rudolph Giuliani. Political pundits, the day after, referred to the Crown Heights affair as central to his defeat.
After serving his term as New York City mayor, Dinkins accepted a faculty appointment in the Practice of Public Affairs at Columbia University's School of International and Public Affairs; he also serves on its board of advisors. Mr. Dinkins chairs the New York City and Johannesburg Sister City Program, serves on the Advisory Board of Independent News and Media, and is a member of the Council on Foreign Relations. He serves on the steering committee of the Association for a Better New York (ABNY), and is a member of the Board of Directors of the Upper Manhattan Empowerment Zone.
Scope and Content
These records originate from the office David N. Dinkins. The documents that comprise this collection primarily encompass the years in which David Dinkins served as mayor of New York City and Manhattan Borough President. The campaign for Manhattan borough president in 1985 and the mayoral campaigns of 1989 and 1993 figure prominently. The corpus consists primarily of correspondence, press releases, news clippings, memoranda, photographs, trophies, awards, diskettes, certificates, pamphlets, pins, drawings, paintings and caricatures. Photographs, drawings, and other ephemera that chronicled Dinkins term as mayor were later added to the collection, but were not separately accessioned.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I: Campaigns and Political Career, 1965-1994
Subseries I.1: General, 1965-1986
Subseries I.2: Campaigns, 1965-1994
Subseries I.3: Manhattan Borough President, 1981-1993
Subseries I.4: Mayoral, 1989-1993
Series II: Memorabilia, 1947-2001
Series III: Photographs, 1941-1994
Series IV: Audio and Visual Materials, 1983-1993
Subjects
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity.; Association of the Bar of the City of New York.; Community Service Society of New York.; Gracie Mansion (New York, N.Y.); Harlem Urban Development Corporation.; League of Women Voters of the City of New York.; Legal Action Center.; Legal Aid Society (New York, N.Y.); National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; New York State Legislative Institute.; Sierra Club--Political activity.; New York (N.Y.)--Campaign Finance Board.; Ali, Muhammad, 1942-; Ashe, Arthur.; Beame, Abraham D. (Abraham David), 1906-2001.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Clinton, Hillary Rodham.; Cuomo, Mario Matthew.; D'Amato, Alfonse.; Horne, Lena.; Jackson, Jesse, 1941-; Kennedy, Edward Moore, 1932-2009.; Koch, Ed, 1924-; Paterson, Basil A.; Rangel, Charles B.; Stein, Andrew J.; Steinem, Gloria.; Sutton, Percy E.; Wonder, Stevie.; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.)--Race relations.; Ellis Island (N.J. and N.Y.); Harlem (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.)--Politics and government.; New York (N.Y.)--Race relations.; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.); African-American mayors.; African-Americans--Politics and government.; Democracy--United States.; Election law--New York (State); Elections--New York (State); Municipal government--New York (State); Political campaigns--New York (State); Race relations.; Representative government and representation--New York (State); Speeches, addresses, etc., American--New York (State); Voter registration--New York (State); Voting--New York (State)
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
David Dinkins Gift 2000
Related Material-- Other Repositories
Archives of David N. Dinkins, 106th Mayor of the City of New York, 1990-1993, New York City Department of Records, Municipal Archives.
- Series I: Campaigns and Political Career, 1965-1994
  This series encompasses David Dinkins early political career, his campaign for Manhattan Borough President, his 1989 and 1993 Mayoral campaigns, and his terms serving as both Manhattan Borough President, 1986-1989, and Mayor of the City of New York, 1990-1993. All four subseries are arranged alphabetically.
  - Subseries I.1: General, 1965-1986
    Subseries I.1: General, 1965-1986, represents his early political career, holding documents from when he served as a representative in the New York State Assembly for one term, 1966-1967, President of the Board of Elections from 1972-1973 and City Clerk, 1975-1985. He was named Deputy Mayor by Mayor Abraham D. Beame (1974-1977), but was not appointed. Dinkins was also a founding member of the Black and Puerto Rican Legislative Caucus of New York State, the Council of Black Elected Democrats of New York State and One Hundred Men. He also served on the Executive Committee of the Association of the Bar of New York State. Materials from all of these organizations are represented here as well. The types of records included in this series are press releases, speeches, meeting minutes, organizational resolutions and by-laws.
    - Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Inc.--Golden Jubilee Dinner Dance and General Membership Meeting, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Assemblyman Elect, 78th District--Statement at Budget Hearing for City Planning Commission, 1965 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Association of the Bar of the City of New York
      - Committee on State Courts of Superior Jurisdiction--Judicial Poll, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Executive Committee
        - Correspondence, Memoranda, Amendments and By-Laws, 1973-1974, (4 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 4 to 7)
        - Agenda, Meetings and Subcommittee on Nominations, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Meetings, Memoranda and Agendas, 1974-1975, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 9 to 10)
        - Meetings, Agendas, Proposed Budget and Nominations, 1973-1976, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 2)
        - Subcommittee on Judiciary and Appeals, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Liaison Between Executive Committee and Committee on Immigration and Nationality Law, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Young Lawyers Committee--Proposal for the Organization of Public Interest Legal Consultant, Inc., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Proposed Bills and Reports Committee Wishes to Publish and Promote, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Proposed Resolution to Establish a Special Committee on Children’s Rights, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Report on Financial Statements, 1975 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Subcommittee on Dues Structure--Reports, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Beame, Abraham D.--Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Black Leadership in New York City, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Black New York--Correspondence and Publication, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1974 March-April (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Audubon Reform Democratic Club, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Carver Democratic Club, 1965-1969, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 15 to 16)
      - Dinkins, David
        - General, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - Withdraws Name From Designation as Deputy Mayor, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - E.E.O. Affirmative Action Group, New Jersey Branch, 1974 June (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Freedom Funds United Foundation, Inc., 1974 July (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Fourth Annual Black Caucus Weekend, 1974 June (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - New York State Assembly, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - State Democratic Committee, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Campaign Financing Call for Reform--Includes Speech With Drafts, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - City Club of New York, 1973 December (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Community Service Society
      - The Urban Future and the Community Service Society, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, Board Meetings, Program Committees and Financial Statements, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Welfare Cost Stabilization Proposal, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Council of Black Elected Democrats
      - Affirmative Action Plan of the Black and Puerto Rican Caucus of the State Legislature, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Meetings, Correspondence, Constitution, Resolution and By-Laws, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Deputy Mayor for Planning--News Clippings, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Emergency Committee on the Energy Crisis--Correspondence, Press Releases and Newsletters, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Emergency Energy Task Force--The City of New York Summary Report, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Harlem Lawyers Association--Proposed Amended By-Laws, 1971 November 5 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Harlem Urban Development Corp.--Correspondence and Memoranda to the Mayor, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Inner City Broadcasting Corp., WLIB--Action Proposals to Purchase WBLS, 1974, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 3 to 4)
    - Invitations and Schedules With Handwritten Notes, 1971-1972, 1974, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Joint Center for Political Studies--The Black Community and Revenue Sharing, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - League of Women Voters of the City of New York--Correspondence and Newsletters, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Legal Action Center of the City of New York--Report on Activities, 1975 March (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Legal Aid Society of New York City
      - Correspondence, Meeting Minutes, Memoranda, Press Releases, News Clippings and Reports, 1975, (5 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 10 to 14)
      - A Description of the Work of the Juvenile Rights Division, 1975 February (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Juvenile Rights Division Newsletters, 1971-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Private Funding Crisis--Memoranda, 1974 November 24 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Legislative Resolution Supporting an Independent Commission on Civil Rights, 1983 June-July (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - The Manhattan Guardsmen, Inc.--Constitution and Meeting Agenda, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Minority Vendors, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Minority Small Business Ownership Training Program, 1971 November 16 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - New School for Social Research, Center for New York City Affairs--"Black Leadership in New York City," David Dinkins, 1986 Fall (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - New York Association of Black Educators, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - New York City Board of Elections
      - Correspondence, Memoranda and News Clippings, Meeting Agenda and Reports, 1971-1975, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 10 to 12)
      - Election Legislation--Handwritten and Typed Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Federal Legislation, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Improvement Project, Press Releases, Correspondence and Memoranda, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - National Voter Registration Act, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Petition Forms, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Primary, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Remarks at the Annual Awards Dinner of the Trenton, New Jersey NAACP, 1973 October 12 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Voter Education, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Voter Registration By Mail--Correspondence, Memoranda and Notes, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - New York City Clerk
      - General, 1978-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 7 to 8)
      - Correspondence, Statements and Press Releases 1978-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 9 to 10)
      - Correspondence, 1982-11985 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Democratic National Convention--Delegate-at-Large, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - The National Urban League--The Julius A. Thomas Society, 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - New York State Assembly--Electoral District Maps, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - New York State Legislative Institute, Baruch College--State of New York Report on the New York State Legislative Research and Training Program, 1975 July (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - One Hundred Black Men, Inc.
      - Article of Incorporation, By-Laws, Mailing Lists and Reports, 1968-1975, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Paterson, Basil--
      - Requests for Employment, Includes Resumes, 1977-1978, (2 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 6 to 7)
      - Requests for Employment, Includes Resumes, 1977-1978, (4 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 1 to 4)
      - Speech Materials With Drafts, 1968-1970, 1973, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 5 to 6)
      - Speech Materials With Drafts, 1968-1970, (2 Folders) (Box 9, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Preliminary Report and Recommendations for Legislation for Consideration by the 1973 Legislation Session of the Joint Legislative Committee, 1972 December 15 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Politics of Government--Course Sessions Held at the Church of Master, Harlem, New York, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Proposal For the Establishment of a Data Center for Political Affairs By the Legislative Institute of the City of New York, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Proposal For the Expansion of Minority Business Opportunity in the State of New York, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Proposal For the Neighborhood Advocacy Complex, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Reveille Club of New York, Inc.--Notice of Regular Meeting, 1973 October 31 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - State Department of Health Care Services--Medi-Cal Contract, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Vulcan Society, Inc. Fire Department, City of New York--Organizational Structure, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - The Washington Heights Neighborhood Family Care Center--Drafts, Memoranda and Press Releases, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - WNET/13 Training School--To Prepare Disadvantaged and Minority Group Members For Entry Into Television and Film Production, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Subseries I.2: Campaigns, 1965-1994
    Subseries I.2: Campaigns, 1965-1994, documents David Dinkins campaigns for Manhattan Borough President in 1985 and both Mayoral Campaigns of 1989 and 1993. It should be noted that there is one file on Dinkins’ first electoral campaign for New York State Assembly in 1965. The bulk of material consists of campaign literature, fundraising events, and volunteers for the Committee for David Dinkins, endorsements by constituency, speeches with drafts, candidate questionnaires with responses, position papers, and strategies by groups, polls and accomplishments. Also prominent are congratulatory correspondence on primary and general elections. Notes of unidentified authorship can be found in abundance throughout this series.
    - New York State Assembly
      - Correspondence, Literature and Press Releases, 1965-1969 (Spanish) (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Manhattan Borough President
      - Absentee Ballots, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Biographical Information and Press Releases, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Block, Herbert--Notes, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Campaign
        - California--Fundraising, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Literature, 1985 (Spanish) (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Materials, 1981-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 7 to 8)
        - Notes, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        - Strategy and Surveys, 1981, 1984-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 10 to 11)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - Campaign, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Education--Student Lists, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Endorsements
        - General, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Clippings, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Lists, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - Jewish, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Farrakhan, Louis--Correspondence, News Clippings and Statements, 1984-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 7 to 8)
      - Friends of David Dinkins, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Fundraising--Volunteers and Donors, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Gay and Lesbian Community, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Housing, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Jewish Breakfast, 1985 August 28 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Lincoln Towers Residents, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Mitchell-Lama Residents, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Nader, Jerry, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - New York Junior Tennis League, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Policy Papers
        - General, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 7)
        - Rent Control, Disabled, Housing and Youth, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 8)
        - Women, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Poll Accessibility, 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Press Releases and Statements, 1981 1985 January-September, (3 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 11 to 13)
      - Record On Issues of Concern to the Jewish Community, 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Speeches With Drafts, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Stein, Andrew--General, 1981-1983, 1987-1993 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Transition to Manhattan Borough President--Includes Policy Planning Retreat, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Mayoral, 1989
      - Abortion--Views, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Affordable Housing, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - AIDS, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Anti-Semitism, 1987-1989 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Apuzzo, William Joseph, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Arts and Letters Committee, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Arab Americans, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Asian Americans for David Dinkins--Includes Correspondence, 1989 (Chinese) (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Assembly District Status Sheets, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Bias Crimes--Correspondence and Statements, 1989 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Bronx, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - The BACA Report on the Latino Voter, 1989, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 2 to 3)
      - Cagan, Leslie, 1984-1989 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Campaign
        - General, 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 5)
        - Clippings, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 6)
        - Committee Structure, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 7)
        - Flyers, 1989, (3 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 8 to 10)
        - Jewish Literature, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 1)
        - Memorabilia, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 2)
        - Newsletters, 1989 (Spanish) (Box 15, Folder 3)
        - Pamphlets, 1989 (Spanish) (Box 15, Folder 4)
        - Strategy, 1989 March (Box 15, Folder 5)
        - Upstart, 1985-1989, (2 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 6 to 7)
      - CBS Exit Polls, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Citizens Committee for Children of New York, Inc., 1989 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Club Briefing, 1989 January-May, (3 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 10 to 12)
      - Coalition for the Homeless, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - College Students, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Constituents, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 2)